[Music]
Hello.
Hey, Air. Uh, you know, when there's a
big event, there's always a few people
who have to warm up the audience. That's
That's how I feel right now. Exactly.
Exactly. Wow. And I like the fact that
they found the only photo of me with a
buttoned shirt in for the intro. So
that's the that's the only button shirt
I own as an engineer. Yeah. The internet
never forgets. That's true. I have my
fair share of people picking up uh
things there as well. So um today we're
going to talk about the AI native deaf
landscape. This is what guy also
mentioned in his keynote. We've been
collecting tools, looking at tools for,
you know, a lot several months right
now. And I think this session is what's
new, what's coming, and it's the great
like intro for the whole uh uh AI tools
in actions because there's so many tools
out there. And then people are really
craving uh to have more tools. If you
haven't done yet, you can see it at
landscape.dev.io. U pay out a visit. Uh
if anything's missing, let us know. All
right.
So, I'm going to kick it off with the
first observation. Um, I was adding
tools to this and they came in and you
think you know a few coding
tools and if like every week there's a
couple of new of them. So, that code
section exploding. I don't know whether
you notice the same thing Amir but like
why is that like why is that like so
unique and and and happening now? So, so
this is very common. So, thank that's a
great question and every time you see um
like a new technology coming up,
developers love it and create a lot of
interesting innovation around it. So, if
you remember when Android was launched,
tons and millions of applications uh
came to fruition. So, we're seeing the
same thing. There's a there's a new
thing in town which is like how can we
use AI in a better way to generate
software and there's tons of tools that
are targeting multiple aspects of
software creation whether it's design
whether it's prototyping whether it's
testing whether it's the IDE and we're
seeing a lot of things happening around
the IDE lately um the the questions that
we need to ask oursel in the future is
like which of these tools are going to
be consolidated and which are these
tools are going to work well together
because if you remember the old days of
every time you had this type of
innovation you have tons of tools but
none of them are connected and you need
to do a lot of um a lot of of um
building yourself and scripting yourself
in order to connect all these tools. So
uh I think the key here is to evaluate
all these and to see what works well
together in a stack.
That's a good observation and I I think
when we initially thought about
categorizing things is oh um this one is
an agent this one is has that it it was
a lot more about the features but what
what happening is because there's so
much fierce competition is that every te
tool is copying whatever cool new
feature the other one. They're all it's
almost like a race to the bottom and
like you say the survival will be the
one that is maybe not the best uh like
ultimate coding tool but the one that
integrates the one that like looks at
the workflow uh and improves that uh in
the whole coding tool. 100% yeah I
totally agree. I think the as an
engineer, I want everything to work
together and to give me the best
interface and the best process and the
best workflow so I can be productive. I
don't need to work for my tools. So
right now you do a lot of working for
your tools in order to connect them all.
But I think that we'll see how prompt
engineering connects to my cursor
connects to my testing. Uh I think that
is the the near future.
Well, you know, it's a it's a period of
chaos like any new technology and uh
this is surfing the wave of innovation.
Exactly. In there indeed.
Um in the last six months, something
that caught everybody's eye was divide
coding, right? that really resonated
although it it is essentially not
something new but you know I had my fair
share in in my life about like having
labels and like people all of a sudden
react to this the reaction to vibe
coding was enormous right like there was
haters there's lovers um in your opinion
like what is it like how does it like
bring value so I think the first thing
is that it's a horrible brand I think
it's a it's a very bad name for some for
something that I think is very useful.
We call it vibe coding because we it's
almost derogatory. It's like yeah, I
have a vibe to code something. But if
you look at it at behind the scene, uh
the actual the actual process is
actually makes a lot of sense. The human
says what they want to do and the and
we're working with the AI. create stuff
and and vibe coding starts with like um
hey the the engineer the person doesn't
know anything about engineering but I'm
an engineer I and I tremendously enjoyed
using vibe coding because I I was more
effective using the vibe coding and to
get the workloads that I wanted to do. I
didn't want to engineer a back-end
service that was infinitely scalable. I
wanted to make a simple page and I and I
didn't want to code it and I sorry I I
don't really like CSS and stuff like
that. So the vibe coding created all
that for me. I'm more of a backend
engineer and it was really really
useful. I would actually call it PM
coding because I think I acted as the PM
in that instance and I told the AI what
to do. Uh last thing I'm going to say
about uh Vibe coding is that they've
solved not just the coding but also the
SRRA job which is really interesting. A
lot of these people it doesn't just
creates the code it also deploys the
code which I think is very interesting
because it takes more of the CI/CD
workloads and automates them for me. So
I don't need to worry about a lot of the
processes of just deploying it and
seeing a and sharing a link to someone
that I want to share this uh thing that
I've created for. Yeah, you know, I'm
all about like operationally and
deploying stuff. So that's great. Uh in
one of my blog articles, I I talk about
the shift from moving from coder to
manager. On the one hand, you're
managing and watching whatever is being
generated, whether that's good or not,
that review process. But also in
production when it fails right like you
are responsible still like and having
that understanding is really key. Uh for
those who don't know the word vibe
coding actually originates a little bit
within the AI engineering world where um
within the community when people were
delivering AI applications and they were
like looks good to me and and like
whenever a new model cames out they
didn't have rigorous testing and the
community started calling this vibe
checks of models and I think that's how
that term kind of got into the vibe
coding uh thing as well. Uh I think it's
so powerful. It's scary at the same
time. Uh but yeah, I I'm I'm hooked. It
gets you into the flow, right? Much like
your coding flow. Um and that's that's
really powerful. Uh and the better the
tools will get uh the better the more
robust uh that would prepare for this.
So definitely v
coding I I don't see it that much as a
scary thing as as others kind of portray
it. Of course, if you don't look at your
code, okay, right? There's scrutiny, but
you're still professional, right? So, if
if that is and I also like the fact that
Karpati brought in maybe uh to do it by
voice, which is another fun thing,
right? I don't know if you heard about
that, but you just talk to the machine,
it just accepts it. I I love that and I
it really resonates what you said about
checking uh and doing the PR uh because
I think you need to use vibe coding
today for certain workloads. I wouldn't
do uh vibe coding today for security and
compliance for example but I'll
definitely do vibe coding for creating a
prototype for a front end or a simple
game. So I think the the more core the
workload is, the more the human needs to
be involved in checking and maintaining
and making sure that it passes not just
the vibe check but also the rigorous
testing that you need to do for some
workloads. But if it's actually for
lightweight workloads, things that you
do for marketing, for example, creating
a web page for marketing, then this is a
great tool for prototyping. And I
believe that the AI will become better
and more proficient in core workloads as
time passes.
Yeah. And that prototyping is key. Like
I I use it many times. You do VIP coding
of a period. You just accept it. But you
actually start understanding the problem
better. So when you're actually going to
do the coding, you have actually
explored the domain. So similar to
exploratory testing, it's like
exploratory coding uh as such. All
right, let's move on to the next big
trend. MCP. It seems like the golden key
or something right now where like
everybody's doing MCP, right? Yes,
everybody's doing everybody's talking
about MCP. Okay. Yeah, I think I think
there's a few uh successful
implementations of MCP. I think Zapier
is doing a very good job there. Um, and
I think that the key here is that
connected systems are I think the most
important thing in modern software like
if you're building software that does
not connect systems, it has a very
limited use. And MCP is the way or at
least the current way to connect between
AI and integrating systems just like API
used to be for uh regular coding that we
used to do. And and I think MCP also is
is a new paradigm that is needs to be
tested. So a lot of my friends have used
MCP and they say, "Hey, it's it's a
great standard and and I love the server
functionality, but it does have a lot of
things that are still missing there."
So, it's als it's it's been in the
market for about a month in in in our
minds uh with a lot maybe a little bit
more with the launch of a few uh popular
MCP servers, but it's still work in
progress. Um that that's my thought
right now. Yeah. Where last year was uh
you know before last year it was all
about making work in vector databases.
Last year was eval and this year it's
everything about MCP and exposing and I
think it's the nice thing is that all
the vendors can bring in their APIs. So
that kind of ecosystem blew up in a way
that you don't have to have an
integration or a plugin or something
within uh the ecosystem of your coding
editors but you can just use start using
the tool. So I I hear what you're
saying. It's not as like the perfect
standard, but at least it's something
that that is being worked on and and
that's why it's so great as uh and it's
being integrated everywhere, right? Yes.
And I think there's like the there's two
levels of of problems here as an
engineer. One of them is to choose the
right system for my for my prompt. So
let's say I have Slack connected and I
have Jira connected. I have multiple
systems in my organization. So the first
level is to choose the the system that I
want to work with. MCP does not solve
that. That's still to be solved. But
once I choose the right uh the right
system, MCP helps me implement what I
want to do as an AI in that system of
record. So I think that's the that's
where MCP is very useful.
Cool. Right. Specifications. Uh maybe
one of the last things we're we're going
to talk about. Um we started not just
doing prompts but like just fit it like
whatever like we writed the
specifications either product or
technical which is also a new trend that
they're all building this kind of in one
form of another uh in there as well. So
um that's just one like for the sake of
time I'll move on to the next one as
well. Autonomous coding agent is
probably where the excitement is and
also guy showed it in his keynote. Um,
yeah, it's headless, it's CLI, it's a
synchronous, and it just does the work,
right? Yeah. I I love that because it
actually adds the aspect to agents that
I've been missing for so long, which is
agency. We've been working with agents,
telling them what to do, not giving them
their own agency to create the things
that they that they need to do. And
coming back to vibe coding, I really
like the fact that when there's an
error, it automatically asks you, hey,
should I check it? Should I fix it? So,
I think the future holds in in systems
that are autonomous that have their own
agency to solve problems. Uh, and and I
think we'll see that in the very near
future.
Yeah. So, you speak already about the
future, right? Yes. We got a lot moving
in in the last six months, right? we got
some new excited integrations and
directions where it's heading. Um, one
interesting question is what are we
still missing, right? What what kind of
do we need? What what's unpolished?
What's kind of like emerging?
Uh, yeah. And I'd love to hear your
thoughts here there as well because I
think you have tons of of experience and
knowledge in this area. What I'm what I
think will happen now is a is an era of
consolidation where a lot of these tools
are going to be connected or acquired by
other companies and we're going to see
more more stacks uh of connected agents
and systems and testing and and uh
basically everything that we had in the
CI/CD pipeline. everything that we had
in the old traditional coding will need
to port in into this new uh way of of
doing things. So I think that's one
thing. The the next thing is that we're
going to go and see more and more core
workloads being implemented with this
method. Right now I'm seeing PC's, proof
of concepts and early stage mockups, but
we're not seeing core workloads. So I
think we're going to see that and with
that more enterprise adoption of these
solutions. So that's that's my bet for
the next six to to 12 months. Yeah, I
definitely hope it's coming to more
enterprises and the scrutiny on there uh
will indeed be key. Um I'm looking
forward
to solving things like uh doing
something on behalf of a user.
Authentication is kind of like something
that's still well authentication is one
thing but access control who gets access
to what what agents like even aviolo
mode what do you resources you're
allowing so I'm getting the vibes of uh
access management control of AWS where
it's like super complex uh to give
access um also kind of that like
synchronous will be fun and um in
general how people build up that trust
like uh what what Kai was saying, we
gotten good
at the like describing what we want and
it gets more context, but I I see kind
of the flip side of this. How do you
actually know and describe what good
looks like? Because now it's generating
and then we have are still the ones that
kind of need to assess it. So now we
need a system that actually judges you
know in the evaluations they call it
like LLM is a judge but we we need
something that actually understands and
on our behalf starts saying this is good
and this is bad not just it runs or the
llinter passes but this is actually what
I meant. So that's that's a lot of
exploration um to be common. So, you
know, the next six months at the next
event,
air, let's see where we came from. And
uh I I thank you for just sharing your
thoughts and uh just an exciting space.
So, yeah. And I guess now it's over back
to that, right? And enjoy the rest of
the track.
Thank you so